we can now move to the application input output
interface so we're going to talk about drivers
now this part of the lecture it's basically
a discussion about why it is challenging for
the operating system to interact to keep track
of the different or interact with the different
devices despite the fact that eventually we
need drivers to communicate
with each specific device so as I mentioned
in the beginning of this lecture but also of
this cause the operating system needs to abstract
away the specific detailed differences
between each type of device and just generalize
them
so there is a keyboard there is a mouse
there is a disk and so on as you can imagine
the reason why you want to do this is that
you cannot maintain an operating system in
which you have dedicated code that is specific
to interact with specific type of
disks of specific keyboards
and so on you need to decouple a bit the
abstraction of a certain type of device
with the actual implementation and the actual
device you are going to use and this is what
you do by using basically drivers
you create a separation layer between what
the operating system sees as a keyboard and
what you are actually using as a keyboard
and the way you communicate with your actual
device the point I'm trying to make here is
that even in such a case finding what are
the dimensions along which you can categorize
the different types
of hardware it's not a trivial task so
this is how it looks like this is what I just
said so you have the kernel you have the
portion of it the subsystem that is about
managing input output
and eventually at the lower level you will
have drivers from the operating system perspective
these are abstractions of the specific type
of device you are trying to communicate with
so you can have one for the mouse one for the keyboard
then you have the ones for the
SCSI drivers and then you have the actual specific
driver that is the one that will take care
of the communication with the physical hardware
you install on your machine so why is it challenging
still to characterize the different types
of devices you have?
well you can look here at some aspects you could
use to classify them and you can see that
each one of them has different properties
along these dimensions so you can take into
account the mode in which they transfer data
if it's individual characters or if it's blocks
the access method if it's sequential only
or if it can be random the schedule with which
you can manage transfers so whether you can
have basically synchronous or asynchronous
communication you have devices that can be
shared and devices that cannot be
shared
they are dedicated it can only be used by
one process at the time or one task at the time they can
perform one task at a time of course they have different
speeds and you have different latency seek
time for example if you are using a rotating
disc or an SSD and you can also classify
them based on the direction of the input output
so whether they are only input only output or if they
can do both things so this is just what
I just said this is pretty simple to follow
I think so let's just have a look at some
types of devices along with these dimensions
we can use to classify them so we have devices
that communicate using blocks
so block devices we discussed this
when we were talking about file systems so
when you communicate with the disk you basically
exchange blocks and then you have other devices
like the keyboard or the mouse in which you
actually have exchanges that are of smaller
sizes
they are of individual characters so you can
imagine that the operating system needs to
provide different APIs you can
have read write and seek for a block device
and you would probably have a get and put
that are for sequential ordered interaction
with character devices
when you want to share data with a disk
or when you are reading data from the keyboard
you can imagine that this is completely different
from actually communicating data or getting
data through the network here you cannot really
have a random access because you can only get
the next
portion of bytes that you are retrieving to
the network or the next portion of bytes through
the network so in that case the operating
system needs a different interface for network
devices that it uses for disks for example
so you can have read and write API for example
then you have completely different types of
devices that are clocks
and timers so you will probably need to define
APIs that they can use either to keep track
of the elapsed time or basically the current
time but also to set triggers when a certain
amount of time expires and we discussed
this when we were discussing
scheduling you want the operating system
to wake up periodically to take scheduling
decisions independently of the processes you
are running and whether they are going back
into ready or waiting state and to do
you use specific pieces of hardware that are
the clocks of the computers basically
then another thing you can think about when
you are designing an operating system and
you are designing the way in which you can
communicate with for example block devices
is the type of communication you have so you
can have blocking or nonblocking, blocking
basically means that you can create APIs that
will suspend the execution of
the process as soon as that process is trying
for example to write something to disk or read something
from the disk or some other device it's
easier to go for a blocking API because
it's easier to maintain code and also write applications
that are blocking you don't have the problem
of defining code that can keep executing despite
the
fact that it needs some information that needs
to be notified when that information is available
for example when a certain amount of data
has been written disk or it's available
from the disk you can create nonblocking
versions of the APIs and the operating system
level by having multithreaded executions in
which you transfer the data from
the thread that is requesting let's say to
write something to a different thread and
then you allow this second thread to block
so the operating system can of course APIs
that are nonblocking by maintaining internally
its own
extra threads and managing the transfer
to disks with these threads rather than the
specific threads that are executing on
let's say the user processes then
of course aside from blocking and nonblocking
you can also have true asynchronous APIs
so in that case if the hardware supports asynchronous
input and output then you can make more performant
operating system that is also more complicated
of course to define and to develop that will
use signals and share the signals with the threads
of the user's processes whenever a synchronous
input output request has been handled by
the hardware